Guide to the Bruce Rogers Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Bruce Rogers collection
1895-1965
GEN MSS 824
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection contains letters to and from Bruce Rogers, four compositions by Rogers, and two writings about Rogers. Among others, the correspondents include the artists Valenti Angelo and Rudolph Ruzicka, author Alfred W. Pollard, printers and publishers Emily E. Connor, Geoffrey Cumberlege, and Stone and Kimball, and various collectors and friends including Alfred and Florence Howell and H. M. Marvin, Rogers' friend and physician. Writings include two speeches, one poem, and one essay by Rogers, a master's thesis on Rogers by Georgia Mansbridge, and a brief memoir by H. M. Marvin.
Rogers, Bruce, 1870-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of H. M. Marvin, 1961 and 1966. Gift of Georgia Mansbridge, 1965. Purchased from Howard S. Mott, Inc., on the Naphtali Daggett Fund, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Bruce Rogers (1870-1957)
American typographer, type designer, and book designer.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains letters to and from Bruce Rogers, four compositions by Rogers, and two writings about Rogers. The correspondents include the artists Valenti Angelo and Rudolph Ruzicka, author Alfred W. Pollard, printers and publishers Emily E. Connor, Geoffrey Cumberlege, and Stone and Kimball, and various collectors and friends including Alfred and Florence Howell and H. M. Marvin, Rogers' friend and physician. Writings include two speeches, one poem, and one essay by Rogers, a master's thesis on Rogers by Georgia Mansbridge, and a brief memoir by H. M. Marvin.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1895-1956. II. Writings, 1942-1965.
Book designers; Typographers; Masters theses; Book designers; Typographers; Angelo, Valenti, 1897-1982; Armitage, Merle, 1893-1975; Blodgett, Glen Walton; Connor, Emily E.; Cumberlege, Geoffrey; Esarey, Logan, 1874-1942; Howell, Alfred C. (Alfred Corey), -1961; Howell, Florence, 1869-1946; Kent, Henry Watson, 1866-1948; Mansbridge, Georgia; Marvin, H. M. (Harold Myers), 1893-1977; Merryweather, John; Pollard, Alfred W. (Alfred William), 1859-1944; Rogers, Bruce, 1870-1957; Ruzicka, Rudolph, 1883-1978; Sayle, Charles, 1864-1924; Caxton Club; Marchbanks Press; Stone & Kimball
- Correspondence, 1895-1956; Series I; 17
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence between Bruce Rogers and colleagues including authors, printers, designers, collectors, and friends.
  - Letters (10) and Christmas card to Valenti Angelo; two envelopes bear Rogers' cameo stamp likeness, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of H. M. Marvin, 1961
  - Letter to Merle Armitage, re: The Twelve Moneths, and private presses, 1950 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Removed from The Twelve Moneths and Christmas Day from "Fantastickes," by Nicholas Breton (BEIN X178 R63 Z951B, Copy 2); gift of H. M. Marvin
  - Letter to Glen Walton Blodgett, re: autograph, 1927 Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of H. M. Marvin, 1966
  - Letter to Mrs. Burgess, re: project and W. A. Dwiggins, 1925 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchased from Howard S. Mott, Inc., on the Naphtali Daggett Fund, 1995
  - Letters (3) to Emily E. Connor, Marchbanks Press, re: "The Camp Steele Alphabet" pamphlet published by the Portfolio Club, with autograph manuscript essay for the pamphlet, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters (13) to Emily E. Connor, Marchbanks Press, re: Logan Esarey's The Indiana Home, published by Indiana University Press, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters (8) to Emily E. Connor, Marchbanks Press, re: Selections from the Life and Writings of Saint Francis of Assisi, published by the Rowfant Club, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter from Geoffrey Cumberlege, Oxford University Press, re: new edition of T. E. Lawrence's Odyssey, 1934 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters (8) to Alfred, Florence, and Janet Howell; with two poems by Rogers, and two letters from Rudolph Ruzicka to Alfred C. Howell, 1943-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Source unknown
  - Letter to Helen M. Lohmann, with proof print of heraldic device, 1948 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters and postcards (14) to H. M. (Harold Myers) Marvin, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter from John Merryweather, Caxton Club, re: prospectus for Ricketts manuscript, 1942 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Postcard to Myra A. Pierson, 1936 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters (4) from Alfred W. Pollard, re: The Trained Printer and the Amateur, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter from Rudolph Ruzicka, regarding design for a bookplate for Philip Hofer, 1937 Apr 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter to Charles Edward Sayle, thanking him for a book, 1919 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter to Stone & Kimball, re: sketches for binding, 1895 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Writings, 1942-1965; Series II; 5
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by author.
  The series contains four compositions by Bruce Rogers, one by Georgia Mansbridge, and one by H. M. Marvin.
  - Mansbridge, Georgia, "Bruce Rogers, American Typographer: a study of his life and career"; typescript carbon in blue cloth binder, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Gift of Georgia Mansbridge, 1965
    General note
    Typescript of master's thesis for Southern Connecticut State College; former call number: MS Vault Shelves Rogers
  - Marvin, H. M., memoir of conversation with Rogers about printing inks; typescript, with autograph manuscript note from Rogers, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rogers, Bruce, acceptance speech upon receiving gold medal from the American Academy of Arts and Letters; typescript, signed; with carbon transcript, explanatory note by Harold Marvin, and print made by Rogers from the engraved edge of the medal, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rogers, Bruce, acceptance speech upon receiving the first Aldus award from the Limited Editions Club; typescript; with explanatory note by Harold Marvin and invitation to award dinner, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rogers, Bruce, "Kalligraphic Kent"; New Year's poem about Henry Watson Kent; typescript signed, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Rogers, Bruce, "The Story of the BRible, The Last Book of Rogers, called JE NE SUIS"; autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)